Mathias Ruoss

Data Scientist with a Master in Quantitative Finance from ETH Zurich

Passionate about programming, data science and statistics. I like to invest in well-written code and with 4+ years of experience in software engineering in Python, I look forward to contributing to your team!



mathias.ruoss@outlook.com

Zurich, Switzerland

in linkedin.com/in/mathiasruoss

+41 76 377 01 95

👿 maruoss.github.io

github.com/maruoss

WORK EXPERIENCE

Data Science Intern Swiss National Bank (SNB)

09/2023 - 09/2024

Zurich, Switzerland

- Constructed end-to-end ML pipelines using Python
- Optimized models to enhance forecast accuracy using mlflow
- Implemented CI/CD pipelines in gitlab (automated testing, static code analysis, package deployment on internal pypi mirror)
- Reviewed, debugged (VSCode IDE) and tested code using pytest

Contact: Dr. Helge Liebert - helge.liebert@snb.ch

Equity Derivatives Sales Intern UBS AG

03/2019 - 08/2019

Opfikon, Zurich, Switzerland

- Priced and designed structured products
- Streamlined operations through automation using Microsoft VBA
- Enhanced trading support by dilligently monitoring market making quotes
- Conducted competitor analysis and executed innovative strategies

Contact: Jérôme Allet - jerome.allet@ubs.com

Reporting Specialist **UBS AG**

12/2013 - 07/2015

Zurich, Switzerland

- Gap year for personal growth and exploration before university studies
- Served as Deputy Product Specialist for the Spanish tax report
- Developed automated tax reports for international clients

EDUCATION

Master of Science, Quantitative Finance ETH Zurich

09/2019 - 02/2023

Zurich, Switzerland

• Thesis: Option Return Classification with Machine Learning (5.75/6.0)

• Thesis: Betting against Beta -

and Bond Market (6.0/6.0)

Evidence from the Swiss Stock

Relevant Courses: Introduction to ML, Advanced ML, Probabilistic AI, Deep Learning, Finance and ML, Mathematical Foundations for Finance

Bachelor of Arts, Banking and Finance University of Zurich

09/2015 - 12/2018

 Semester Award Fall 2018, awarded CHF 600.- for outstanding Bachelor Thesis

Zurich, Switzerland

SKILLS

Programming: Python (4+ y), Git, SQL, C++, R

ML toolkit: numpy, pandas, scikit-learn, matplotlib, seaborn, xgboost, pytorch, mlflow



SW development in Python: IDE (VS Code), debugging, testing/linting/type checks





Statistics and math









Project management

ML PROJECTS

Time Series Forecasting of Swiss CPI Diesel/ Petrol Index (2024)

Time Series Forecasting of Swiss Rental Prices (2024)

Option Return Classification with ML (2023)

Polynomial Feature Learning (2022)

Deep RL applied to Stock Trading (2021)

Road Segmentation with CNNs (2021)

LANGUAGES

English (fluent)

German (native)

French









HOBBIES

Basketball, Football, Gym, Cooking, Hiking, **Exploring Cities**